[AC9E3LA01] (Year 3) understand that cooperation with others depends on shared understanding of social conventions, including turn-taking language, which vary according to the degree of formality
[AC9E3LA02] (Year 3) understand how the language of evaluation and emotion, such as modal verbs, can be varied to be more or less forceful
[AC9E3LA03] (Year 3) describe how texts across the curriculum use different language features and structures relevant to their purpose
[AC9E3LA04] (Year 3) understand that paragraphs are a key organisational feature of the stages of written texts, grouping related information together
[AC9E3LA05] (Year 3) identify the purpose of layout features in print and digital texts and the words used for navigation
[AC9E3LA06] (Year 3) understand that a clause is a unit of grammar usually containing a subject and a verb that need to agree
[AC9E3LA07] (Year 3) understand how verbs represent different processes for doing, feeling, thinking, saying and relating
[AC9E3LA08] (Year 3) understand that verbs are anchored in time through tense
[AC9E3LA09] (Year 3) identify how images extend the meaning of a text
[AC9E3LA10] (Year 3) extend topic-specific and technical vocabulary and know that words can have different meanings in different contexts
[AC9E3LA11] (Year 3) understand that apostrophes signal missing letters in contractions, and apostrophes are used to show singular and plural possession
[AC9E3LE01] (Year 3) discuss characters, events and settings in different contexts in literature by First Nations Australian, and wide-ranging Australian and world authors and illustrators
[AC9E3LE02] (Year 3) discuss connections between personal experiences and character experiences in literary texts and share personal preferences
[AC9E3LE03] (Year 3) discuss how an author uses language and illustrations to portray characters and settings in texts, and explore how the settings and events influence the mood of the narrative
[AC9E3LE04] (Year 3) discuss the effects of some literary devices used to enhance meaning and shape the readerÆs reaction, including rhythm and onomatopoeia in poetry and prose
[AC9E3LE05] (Year 3) create and edit imaginative texts, using or adapting language features, characters, settings, plot structures and ideas encountered in literary texts
[AC9E3LY01] (Year 3) recognise how texts can be created for similar purposes but different audiences
[AC9E3LY02] (Year 3) use interaction skills to contribute to conversations and discussions to share information and ideas
[AC9E3LY03] (Year 3) identify the audience and purpose of imaginative, informative and persuasive texts through their use of language features and/or images
[AC9E3LY04] (Year 3) read a range of texts using phonic, semantic and grammatical knowledge to read accurately and fluently, re-reading and self-correcting when required
[AC9E3LY05] (Year 3) use comprehension strategies when listening and viewing to build literal and inferred meaning, and begin to evaluate texts by drawing on a growing knowledge of context, text structures and language features
[AC9E3LY06] (Year 3) plan, create, edit and publish imaginative, informative and persuasive written and multimodal texts, using visual features, appropriate form and layout, with ideas grouped in simple paragraphs, mostly correct tense, topic-specific vocabulary and correct spelling of most high-frequency and phonetically regular words
[AC9E3LY07] (Year 3) plan, create, rehearse and deliver short oral and/or multimodal presentations to inform, express opinions or tell stories, using a clear structure, details to elaborate ideas, topic-specific and precise vocabulary, visual features, and appropriate tone, pace, pitch and volume
[AC9E3LY08] (Year 3) write words using joined letters that are clearly formed and consistent in size
[AC9E3LY09] (Year 3) understand how to apply knowledge of phonemeûgrapheme (soundûletter) relationships, syllables, and blending and segmenting to fluently read and write multisyllabic words with more complex letter patterns
[AC9E3LY10] (Year 3) understand how to apply knowledge of common base words, prefixes, suffixes and generalisations for adding a suffix to a base word to read and comprehend new multimorphemic words
[AC9E3LY11] (Year 3) use phonemeûgrapheme (soundûletter) relationships and less common letter patterns to spell words
[AC9E3LY12] (Year 3) recognise and know how to write most high-frequency words including some homophones
