--- Extracting c:\Users\dsuth\Documents\Joshua\Year34_English_Sequence\K-6 3-4 English Unit 1 Plan 26 .docx ---
--- Tables ---
Year level - 3 & 4                K-6 Unit 1 | Unit Title û Examining and creating imaginative literary texts | Duration of Unit û Term 4û 10 Weeks
Year 4
Overview of Unit | Students engage with a variety of texts for enjoyment, including short chapter fiction books, picture books, print, digital and oral texts. Texts include classic or contemporary literature by Australian and world authors, including texts from and about Asia, and the oral narrative traditions and literature of First Nations Australians. Texts describe sequences of events and unusual happenings, and support or extend students as independent readers. Students describe how ideas are developed through characters and events and how texts reflect contexts.  Students use these texts as models to create imaginative adaptations of a narrative and discuss their ideas.
Assessment (summative) û what is being assessed | Assessment: 1.1 Responding to literature Assessment purpose: To read, view and comprehend an imaginative text. To create a written and/or multimodal imaginative text developing storylines, characters and settings.
Achievement Standard û  The bolded coloured aspects of the achievement standard are summatively assessed in this unit. Monitoring strategies for this unit have been identified in the underlined achievement standard aspects. | Year 4  Speaking and listening By the end of Year 4, students interact with others, and listen to and create spoken and/or multimodal texts including stories. They share and extend ideas, opinions and information with audiences, using relevant details from learnt topics, topics of interest or texts. They use text structures to organise and link ideas. They use language features including subjective and objective language, topic-specific vocabulary and literary devices, and/or visual features and features of voice.  Reading and viewing They read, view and comprehend texts created to inform, influence and/or engage audiences. They describe how ideas are developed including through characters and events, and how texts reflect contexts. They describe the characteristic features of different text structures. They describe how language features including literary devices, and visual features shape meaning. They read fluently and accurately, integrating phonic, morphemic, grammatical and punctuation knowledge.   Writing and creating They create written and/or multimodal texts including stories for purposes and audiences, where they develop ideas using details from learnt topics, topics of interest or texts. They use paragraphs to organise and link ideas. They use language features including complex sentences, topic-specific vocabulary and literary devices, and/or visual features. They write texts using clearly formed letters with developing fluency. They spell words including multisyllabic and multimorphemic words with irregular spelling patterns, using phonic, morphemic and grammatical knowledge.
Year 4
Content descriptions that guide teaching and learning leading to the assessment | Language Language for interacting with others explore language used to develop relationships in formal and informal situations (AC9E4LA01) Monitoring strategy û Speaking and listening identify the subjective language of opinion and feeling, and the objective language of factual reporting AC9E4LA02   Text structure and organisation identify how texts across the curriculum have different language features and are typically organised into characteristic stages depending on purposes (AC9E4LA03) Reading & viewing Writing & creating identify how text connectivesùincluding temporal and conditional wordsùand topic word associations are used to sequence and connect ideas (AC9E4LA04) Reading & viewing Writing & creating identify text navigation features of online texts that enhance readability including headlines, drop-down menus, links, graphics and layout AC9E4LA05 Reading & viewing  Language for expressing and developing ideas understand that complex sentences contain one independent clause and at least one dependent clause, typically joined by a subordinating conjunction, to create relationships such as time and causality (AC9E4LA06) Writing & creating investigate how quoted (direct) and reported (indirect) speech are used (AC9E4LA07) Writing & creating understand how adverb groups/phrases and prepositional phrases work in different ways to provide circumstantial details about an activity (AC9E4LA08) Writing & creating understand past, present and future tenses and their impact on meaning in a sentence (AC9E4LA09) Writing & creating explore the effect of choices when framing an image, placement of elements in the image and salience on composition of still and moving images in texts AC9E4LA10 Reading & viewing Writing & creating expand vocabulary by exploring a range of synonyms and antonyms, and using words encountered in a range of sources (AC9E4LA11) understand that punctuation signals dialogue through quotation marks and that dialogue follows conventions for the use of capital letters, commas and boundary punctuation (AC9E4LA12) Writing & creating Monitoring strategy -Reading & viewing
Content descriptions that guide teaching and learning leading to the assessment | Literature Literature and contexts recognise similar storylines, ideas and relationships in different contexts in literary texts by First Nations Australian, and wide-ranging Australian and world authors (AC9E4LE01) Reading & viewing    Engaging with and responding to literature  describe the effects of text structures and language features in literary texts when responding to and sharing opinions (AC9E4LE02) Examining literature discuss how authors and illustrators make stories engaging by the way they develop character, setting and plot tensions (AC9E4LE03) Reading & viewing   examine the use of literary devices and deliberate word play in literary texts, including poetry, to shape meaning (AC9E4LE04) Reading and viewing Monitoring strategy -Speaking & listening Creating literature  create and edit literary texts by developing storylines, characters and settings (AC9E4LE05) Writing & creating Monitoring strategy -Speaking & listening
Content descriptions that guide teaching and learning leading to the assessment | Literacy  Texts in context compare texts from different times with similar purposes and audiences to identify similarities and differences in their depictions of events (AC9E4LY01) Reading and viewing Interacting with others  listen for key points and information to carry out tasks and contribute to discussions, acknowledging another opinion, linking a response to the topic, and sharing and extending ideas and information (AC9E4LY02) Monitoring strategy -Speaking & listening Analysing, interpreting and evaluating identify the characteristic features used in imaginative, informative and persuasive texts to meet the purpose of the text (AC9E4LY03)Reading and viewing read different types of texts, integrating phonic, semantic and grammatical knowledge to read accurately and fluently, re-reading and self-correcting when needed (AC9E4LY04) Reading and viewing Monitoring strategy -Reading & viewing use comprehension strategies such as visualising, predicting, connecting, summarising, monitoring and questioning to build literal and inferred meaning, to expand topic knowledge and ideas, and evaluate texts (AC9E4LY05) Reading and viewing Monitoring strategy -Speaking & listening Creating texts  plan, create, edit and publish written and multimodal imaginative, informative and persuasive texts, using visual features, relevant linked ideas, complex sentences, appropriate tense, synonyms and antonyms, correct spelling of multisyllabic words and simple punctuation (AC9E4LY06) Writing and creating plan, create, rehearse and deliver structured oral and/or multimodal presentations to report on a topic, tell a story, recount events or present an argument using subjective and objective language, complex sentences, visual features, tone, pace, pitch and volume (AC9E4LY07) Monitoring strategy -Speaking & listening write words using clearly formed joined letters, with developing fluency and automaticity (AC9E4LY08) Phonic and word knowledge understand how to use and apply phonological and morphological knowledge to read and write multisyllabic words with more complex letter combinations, including a variety of vowel sounds and known prefixes and suffixes (AC9E4LY09) Monitoring strategy -Reading & viewing understand how to use knowledge of letter patterns, including double letters, spelling generalisations, morphological word families, common prefixes and suffixes, and word origins, to spell more complex words (AC9E4LY10) read and write high-frequency words including homophones and know how to use context to identify the correct spelling (AC9E4LY11) Monitoring strategy -Reading & viewing
Moderation û identify opportunities to moderate at multiple junctures (when/who with/ what / next steps etc) | Before (before assessment takes place and at the planning stage)  Week 5  (Week 8 Term 3)  Aligning targeted aspects of the achievement standard being assessed with appropriate curriculum elements.  Calibrating understandings about how to make judgements using sample student or teacher created sample responses to summative assessment.  Quality assuring the teaching and learning sequence and reviewing the selection of pedagogical approaches, practices and teaching strategies to differentiate teaching and learning. | End (Engaging in moderation processes at the End of the reporting period.) Calibrating judgements for reporting by grading sample assessment folios, representing evidence at, above and below the æCÆ standard.    Confirming judgements for reporting by moderating sample student assessment folios, representing evidence at æAÆ, æBÆ, æCÆ, æDÆ, æEÆ (oráequivalent) level of achievement û against the targeted aspects of the achievement standard taught and assessed in the reporting period.   Using calibrated and confirmed understandings about making standards-based judgements on folios to ensure accuracy of judgements for reporting on student achievement for all students.
Week 3 û Monday Moderation of Unit 3 task  Coominya SS 3:30pm   Week 5 û Moderation /negotiated time   Calibrating understandings about how to make judgements using sample student or teacher created sample responses to summative assessment
What do my students need to be able to do?
Error reading c:\Users\dsuth\Documents\Joshua\Year34_English_Sequence\K-6 3-4 English Unit 1 Plan 26 .docx: 'charmap' codec can't encode character '\u2011' in position 1219: character maps to <undefined>
--- Extracting c:\Users\dsuth\Documents\Joshua\Year34_English_Sequence\p-6cpm_eng_v9_y04_u1_at1-1.docx ---
Error reading c:\Users\dsuth\Documents\Joshua\Year34_English_Sequence\p-6cpm_eng_v9_y04_u1_at1-1.docx: 'charmap' codec can't encode character '\u202f' in position 90: character maps to <undefined>
