--- Extracting Units/HASS/HASS_Y06_YearLevelPlan.docx ---
Coverage of achievement standard in Year 6 Humanities and Social Sciences
The requirements for assessment are specified in the Pû12 curriculum, assessment and reporting framework with additional information provided in the Providing the Australian Curriculum in Prep to Year 10 in Queensland state schools from 2017, Determining implementation approaches for provision of the whole Australian Curriculum in Prep to Year 10 and Assessment and moderation in Prep to Year 10.
Year plans are mechanisms for ensuring coverage of all aspects of the relevant achievement standards for each learning area and/or subject in Prep to Year 10.
Summative assessment is planned in the year and/or band plans to show:
how students will have the opportunity to demonstrate all aspects of the relevant achievement standards for each learning area and/or subject in each year and/or band; and
whether there are multiple opportunities to gather evidence using a range and balance of summative assessment. This should ensure the assessment conventions (technique, type of text, mode, and conditions) are appropriate to the learning area and/or subject and suitable for equitable access for all students.
C2C HASS units were written to assess the learning area achievement standards and teach the aligned Humanities and Social Sciences content.
For further information, visit the Implement the Australian Curriculum Hub.
Note: The mapping of the coverage of achievement standard has been informed by the C2C Guide to making judgments for the unit.
A tick indicates that the summative assessment is aligned to the aspects of the learning area achievement standard.
An asterisk indicates that only part of the aspect of the achievement standard has been assessed.
Content descriptions for Year 6 Humanities and Social Sciences
Review for balance and coverage of content descriptions
The Humanities and Social Sciences content descriptions guide teaching and learning leading to summative assessment against the learning area achievement standard.
--- Tables ---
Year level plan | Humanities and Social Sciences (HASS) | Year level | Year 6
---
Year level description | Australia in the past and present and its connections with a diverse world The Year 6 curriculum focuses on the social, economic and political development of Australia as a nation, particularly after 1900, and AustraliaÆs role within a diverse and interconnected world today. Students explore the events and developments that shaped Australia as a democratic nation and stable economy, and the experiences of the diverse groups who have contributed to and are/were affected by these events and developments, past and present. Students investigate the importance of rights and responsibilities and informed decision-making, at the personal level of consumption and civic participation, and at the national level through studies of economic, ecological and government processes and systems. In particular, students examine AsiaÆs natural, demographic and cultural diversity, with opportunities to understand their connections to Asian environments. These studies enable students to understand how they are interconnected with diverse people and places across the globe. The content provides opportunities for students to develop humanities and social sciences understanding through key concepts including significance; continuity and change; cause and effect; place and space; interconnections; roles, rights and responsibilities; and perspectives and action. These concepts may provide a focus for inquiries and be investigated across sub-strands or within a particular sub-strand context. The content at this year level is organised into two strands: knowledge and understanding, and inquiry and skills. The knowledge and understanding strand draws from four sub-strands: history, geography, civics and citizenship and economics and business. These strands (knowledge and understanding, and inquiry and skills) are interrelated and have been developed to be taught in an integrated way, which may include integrating with content from the sub-strands and from other learning areas, and in ways that are appropriate to specific local contexts. The order and detail in which they are taught are programming decisions. Inquiry Questions A framework for developing studentsÆ knowledge, understanding and skills is provided by inquiry questions. The following inquiry questions allow for connections to be made across the sub-strands and may be used or adapted to suit local contexts: inquiry questions are also provided for each sub-strand that may enable connections within the humanities and social sciences learning area or across other learning areas. How have key figures, events and values shaped Australian society, its system of government and citizenship? How have experiences of democracy and citizenship differed between groups over time and place, including those from and in Asia? How has Australia developed as a society with global connections, and what is my role as a global citizen?
Achievement standard | By the end of Year 6, students explain the significance of an event/development, an individual and/or group. They identify and describe continuities and changes for different groups in the past and present. They describe the causes and effects of change on society. They compare the experiences of different people in the past. Students describe, compare and explain the diverse characteristics of different places in different locations from local to global scales. They describe how people, places, communities and environments are diverse and globally interconnected and identify the effects of these interconnections over time. Students explain the importance of people, institutions and processes to AustraliaÆs democracy and legal system. They describe the rights and responsibilities of Australian citizens and the obligations they may have as global citizens. Students recognise why choices about the allocation of resources involve trade-offs. They explain why it is important to be informed when making consumer and financial decisions. They identify the purpose of business and recognise the different ways that businesses choose to provide goods and services. They explain different views on how to respond to an issue or challenge. Students develop appropriate questions to frame an investigation. They locate and collect useful data and information from primary and secondary sources. They examine sources to determine their origin and purpose and to identify different perspectives in the past and present. They interpret data to identify, describe and compare distributions, patterns and trends, and to infer relationships, and evaluate evidence to draw conclusions. Students sequence information about events, the lives of individuals and selected phenomena in chronological order and represent time by creating timelines. They organise and represent data in a range of formats, including large- and small-scale maps, using appropriate conventions. They collaboratively generate alternative responses to an issue, use criteria to make decisions and identify the advantages and disadvantages of preferring one decision over others. They reflect on their learning to propose action in response to an issue or challenge and describe the probable effects of their proposal. They present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, mapping, graphing, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms.
---
Unit 1: Australia in the past | Unit 2: Australians as global citizens | Unit 3: Australia in a diverse world
Unit overview | Inquiry question: How have key figures, events and values shaped Australian society, its system of government and citizenship? In this unit, students: examine the key figures, events and ideas that led to AustraliaÆs Federation and constitution recognise the contribution of individuals and groups to the development of Australian society since Federation investigate the key institutions, people and processes of AustraliaÆs democratic and legal system locate, collect and interpret information from primary sources sequence information about events and the lives of individuals in chronological order develop arguments use criteria to make decisions and judgments work in groups to generate responses to issues and challenges propose action in response to issues and challenges. | Inquiry questions: What does it mean to be an Australian citizen? How have experiences of democracy and citizenship differed between groups over time and place, including those from and in Asia? In this unit, students: recognise the responsibilities of citizens in AustraliaÆs democracy consider the shared values, right and responsibilities of Australian citizenship and obligations that people may have as global citizens identify different points of view examine continuities and changes in the experiences of Australian democracy and citizenship, including the status and rights of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Peoples, women and children investigate stories of groups of people who have migrated to Australia since Federation evaluate the contribution of individuals and groups to the development of Australian society since Federation sequence information about events and represent time by creating timelines present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials. | Inquiry question: How do places, people and cultures differ across the world? In this unit, students: examine the geographical diversity of the Asia region and the location of its major countries in relation to Australia investigate differences in the economic, demographic and social characteristics of countries across the world consider the worldÆs cultural diversity, including that of its indigenous peoples identify AustraliaÆs connections with other countries organise and represent data in large- and small-scale maps using appropriate conventions interpret data to identify, describe and compare distributions and trends present ideas, findings and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, mapping, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms.
General capabilities and cross-curriculum priorities | Opportunities to engage with:
---
Unit 4: AustraliaÆs global connections | Unit 5: Making decisions to benefit my community
Unit overview | Inquiry questions: What are Australia's global connections between people and places? How do people's connections to places affect their perception of them? In this unit, students: identify how AustraliaÆs connections with other countries change people and places recognise the effects that peopleÆs connections with, and proximity to, places throughout the world have on shaping their awareness and opinion of those places develop appropriate questions to frame an investigation locate and collect useful information from primary and secondary sources organise and represent data in a range of formats, using appropriate conventions interpret data to identify patterns and trends, and to infer relationships identify different points of view and solutions to an issue reflect on their learning to propose action in response to an issue or challenge and describe the probable effects of their proposal present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, graphing, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms. | Inquiry questions: How can resources be used to benefit individuals, the community and the environment? In this unit, students: investigate a familiar community or regional economics or business issue that may affect the individual or the local community examine how the concept of opportunity cost involves choices about the alternative use of resources and the need to consider trade-offs identify the effect that consumer and financial decisions can have on the individual, the broader community and the environment recognise the reasons businesses exist and the different ways they provide goods and services present ideas, findings and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms.
General capabilities and cross-curriculum priorities | Opportunities to engage with:
---
Key General capabilities | Cross-curriculum priorities
Literacy | Personal and social capability | Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander histories and cultures
Numeracy | Ethical understanding | Asia and AustraliaÆs engagement with Asia
Information and communication technology  (ICT) capability | Intercultural understanding | Sustainability
Information and communication technology  (ICT) capability | Critical and creative thinking
---
Assessment | Student responses to summative assessment tasks contribute to their assessment folio. It provides evidence of their learning and represents their achievements over reporting period. The assessment folio should include a range and balance of assessments to make valid judgments about whether the student has met the achievement standard.
Assessment | Unit 1: Australia in the past | Unit 2: Australians as global citizens | Unit 3: Australia in a diverse world | Unit 4: AustraliaÆs global connections | Unit 5: Making decisions to benefit my community
Assessment | Assignment/Project Students explain the significance of key people, events, institutions and processes to the development of the Australian nation. The assessment will gather evidence of the studentÆs ability to: explain the significance of an event/development, an individual escribe the causes and effects of change on society explain the importance of people, institutions and processes to AustraliaÆs democracy and legal system locate and collect useful data and information from primary and secondary sources sequence information about events, the lives of individuals in chronological order collaboratively generate alternative responses to an issue, use criteria to make decisions and identify the advantages and disadvantages of preferring one decision over others reflect on learning to propose personal and/or collective action in response to an issue, and predict the probable effects present ideas, viewpoints and conclusions that incorporate source materials, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms. | Exam/Test Students investigate the rights and responsibilities of Australian citizens today and the experiences of Australian democracy and citizenship for different groups in the past. The assessment will gather evidence of the studentÆs ability to: identify and describe continuities and changes for different groups in the past and present describe the causes and effects of change on society compare the experiences of different people in the past describe the rights and responsibilities of Australian citizens and the obligations they may have as global citizens sequence information about events and represent time by creating timelines examine sources to determine their origin and purpose and to identify different perspectives in the past and present present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms. | Assignment/Project Students demonstrate an understanding of the diversity of places by representing and interpreting data and information in a variety of forms. The assessment will gather evidence of the studentÆs ability to: describe, compare and explain the diverse characteristics of different places in different locations from local to global scales describe how people, places, communities and environments are diverse organise and represent data in a range of formats, including large- and small-scale maps, using appropriate conventions interpret data to identify, describe and compare distributions and trends, and to infer relationships, and evaluate evidence to draw conclusions present ideas, findings and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, mapping, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms. | Collection of work Students investigate the effects of trade connections between Australia and Asia. The assessment will gather evidence of the studentÆs ability to: describe how people, places, communities and environments are globally interconnected and identify the effects of these interconnections over time develop appropriate questions to frame an investigation locate and collect useful data and information from primary and secondary sources organise and represent data in a range of formats, using appropriate conventions interpret data to identify, describe and compare patterns and trends and evaluate evidence to draw conclusions reflect on learning to propose action in response to an issue or challenge and describe the probable effects of their proposal present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, graphing, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms. | Supervised assessment Students explain ways that resources can be used to benefit individuals, the community and the environment. The assessment will gather evidence of the studentÆs ability to: recognise why choices about the allocation of resources involve trade-offs explain why it is important to be informed when making consumer and financial decisions identify the purpose of business and recognise the different ways that businesses choose to provide goods and services present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms.
Moderation | Teachers use moderation to support consistency of teacher judgments and comparability of reported results against the relevant achievement standards.
---
Learning area achievement standard | Opportunities to address the learning area achievement standard using C2C units
Aspects of the Year 6 Humanities and Social Sciences  achievement standard | Unit  1 | Unit  2 | Unit  3 | Unit  4 | Unit  5
explain the significance of an event/development, an individual and/or group
identify and describe continuities and changes for different groups in the past and present
describe the causes and effects of change on society
compare the experiences of different people in the past
describe, compare and explain the diverse characteristics of different places in different locations from local to global scales
describe how people, places, communities and environments are diverse and globally interconnected and identify the effects of these interconnections over time
explain the importance of people, institutions and processes to AustraliaÆs democracy and legal system
describe the rights and responsibilities of Australian citizens and the obligations they may have as global citizens
recognise why choices about the allocation of resources involve trade-offs
explain why it is important to be informed when making consumer and financial decisions
identify the purpose of business and recognise the different ways that businesses choose to provide goods and services
explain different views on how to respond to an issue or challenge
develop appropriate questions to frame an investigation
locate and collect useful data and information from primary and secondary sources
examine sources to determine their origin and purpose and to identify different perspectives in the past and present
interpret data to identify, describe and compare distributions, patterns and trends, and to infer relationships, and evaluate evidence to draw conclusions
sequence information about events, the lives of individuals and selected phenomena in chronological order and represent time by creating timelines
organise and represent data in a range of formats, including large- and small-scale maps, using appropriate conventions
collaboratively generate alternative responses to an issue, use criteria to make decisions and identify the advantages and disadvantages of preferring one decision over others
reflect on their learning to propose action in response to an issue or challenge and describe the probable effects of their proposal
present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of communication forms that incorporate source materials, mapping, graphing, communication conventions and discipline-specific terms
---
Humanities and Social Sciences | Each C2C unit aligned to  learning area content
Knowledge and Understanding | Unit 1 | Unit 2 | Unit 3 | Unit 4 | Unit 5
History
Key figures, events and ideas that led to AustraliaÆs Federation and Constitution (ACHASSK134)
Experiences of Australian democracy and citizenship, including the status and rights of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Peoples, migrants, women and children (ACHASSK135)
Stories of groups of people who migrated to Australia since Federation (including from ONE country of the Asia region) and reasons they migrated (ACHASSK136)
The contribution of individuals and groups to the development of Australian society since Federation (ACHASSK137)
Geography
The geographical diversity of the Asia region and the location of its major countries in relation to Australia (ACHASSK138)
Differences in the economic, demographic and social characteristics of countries across the world (ACHASSK139)
The worldÆs cultural diversity, including that of its indigenous peoples (ACHASSK140)
AustraliaÆs connections with other countries and how these change people and places (ACHASSK141)
Civics and citizenship
The key institutions of AustraliaÆs democratic system of government and how it is based on the Westminster system (ACHASSK143)
The roles and responsibilities of AustraliaÆs three levels of government (ACHASSK144)
The responsibilities of electors and representatives in AustraliaÆs democracy (ACHASSK145)
Where ideas for new laws can come from and how they become law (ACHASSK146)
The shared values of Australian citizenship and the formal rights and responsibilities of Australian citizens (ACHASSK147)
The obligations citizens may consider they have beyond their own national borders as active and informed global citizens (ACHASSK148)
Economics and business
How the concept of opportunity cost involves choices about the alternative use of resources and the need to consider trade-offs (ACHASSK149)
The effect that consumer and financial decisions can have on the individual, the broader community and the environment (ACHASSK150)
The reasons businesses exist and the different ways they provide goods and services (ACHASSK151)
Inquiry and skills | Unit 1 | Unit 2 | Unit 3 | Unit 4 | Unit 5
Questioning
Develop appropriate questions to guide an inquiry about people, events, developments, places, systems and challenges (ACHASSI122)
Researching
Locate and collect relevant information and data from primary sources and secondary sources (ACHASSI123)
Organise and represent data in a range of formats including tables, graphs and large- and small-scale maps, using discipline-appropriate conventions (ACHASSI124)
Sequence information about peopleÆs lives, events, developments and phenomena using a variety of methods including timelines (ACHASSI125)
Analysing
Examine primary sources and secondary sources to determine their origin and purpose (ACHASSI126)
Examine different viewpoints on actions, events, issues and phenomena in the past and present (ACHASSI127)
Interpret data and information displayed in a range of formats to identify, describe and compare distributions, patterns and trends, and to infer relationships (ACHASSI128)
Evaluating and reflecting
Evaluate evidence to draw conclusions (ACHASSI129)
Work in groups to generate responses to issues and challenges (ACHASSI130)
Use criteria to make decisions and judgements and consider advantages and disadvantages of preferring one decision over others (ACHASSI131)
Reflect on learning to propose personal and/or collective action in response to an issue or challenge, and predict the probable effects (ACHASSI132)
Communicating
Present ideas, findings, viewpoints and conclusions in a range of texts and modes that incorporate source materials, digital and non-digital representations and discipline-specific terms and conventions (ACHASSI133)
---
